<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gamasutra on glitchwall.com</title>
    <link>http://glitchwall.com/tags/gamasutra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gamasutra on glitchwall.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 21:25:12 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://glitchwall.com/tags/gamasutra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Reinforcement in Games</title>
      <link>http://glitchwall.com/post/random-reinforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 21:25:12 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://glitchwall.com/post/random-reinforcement/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;article-the-power-of-random-reinforcement-http-www-gamasutra-com-blogs-filipwiltgren-20150928-254722-the-power-of-random-reinforcement-php:1a2a2d9aad363bad5fde9f7b42449725&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Article:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/FilipWiltgren/20150928/254722/The_Power_of_Random_Reinforcement.php&#34;&gt;The Power of Random Reinforcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;card-drawing-a-form-of-random-reinforcement:1a2a2d9aad363bad5fde9f7b42449725&#34;&gt;Card-drawing: a Form of Random Reinforcement?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author gives the example of card-drawing, such as that in games like MtG or Hearthstone, as a form of random reinforcement. While I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with the concept, I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought of it in the contexts of MMO loot drops and the &lt;em&gt;gacha&lt;/em&gt; mechanics we so often see now in mobile games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I don&amp;rsquo;t really consider card-drawing as a form of random reinforcemt because that feeling of hoping for a particular outcome isn&amp;rsquo;t very consistent throughout an entire match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of a match, you feel excited as you hope for a good starting hand. And in subsequent card draws, there may be specific scenarios in which you&amp;rsquo;re praying really hard for a specific card(e.g. a good 2-drop, a counter, combo, etc). But notice how the desired card changes from turn to turn, and also that in general, each card draw fills you with &lt;strong&gt;varying intensities&lt;/strong&gt; of anticipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all card draws were created equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps for that reason, Hearthstone may be addictive as a &lt;em&gt;game&lt;/em&gt;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone has ever been addicted to the specific act of &lt;em&gt;drawing cards&lt;/em&gt; itself. (&amp;ldquo;Okay just one more card. Promise.&amp;rdquo;) Contrast this with the just-one-more-try sentiment when playing Blackjack or a slot machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ethics-vs-values:1a2a2d9aad363bad5fde9f7b42449725&#34;&gt;Ethics vs Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the use of random reinforcement in games ethical? I doubt that absolute morality exists, so I tend not to think in those terms these days. Arguments about ethics tend to accomplish very little anyway. Instead, I find it more productive to consider what I value personally, and let these values guide my decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, getting people addicted to gambling, to buying and opening card packs, or to grinding endlessly for loot isn&amp;rsquo;t very admirable. (Again, I&amp;rsquo;m not passing any judgement here; I&amp;rsquo;m merely staing that I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;d like to spend my time and effort on that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, I think about a game like the Binding of Isaac which I&amp;rsquo;ve sunk countless hours into. A big part of its appeal comes from that anticipation before entering an item room or devil room, and knowing that I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; get some super awesome item combo. Most roguelikes, with their random elements, tend to generate similar experiences. That&amp;rsquo;s random reinforcement right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the Binding of Isaac is not just incredibly fun and addictive. It is also a beautiful game. So why is random reinforcement so distasteful in one scenario and yet palatable, even glorified perhaps in the other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it a matter of degree? Of intention? Of context?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Side note: The article mentioned that slot machines very frequently show an &amp;ldquo;almost win&amp;rdquo; oucome. Are the odds actually skewed towards that? That&amp;rsquo;s just crazy manipulative.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>