<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Puzzle on glitchwall.com</title>
    <link>http://glitchwall.github.io/glitchwall_blog/tags/puzzle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Puzzle on glitchwall.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 21:51:19 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://glitchwall.github.io/glitchwall_blog/tags/puzzle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Good Snowman Is Hard To Build</title>
      <link>http://glitchwall.github.io/glitchwall_blog/post/a-good-snowman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 21:51:19 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://glitchwall.github.io/glitchwall_blog/post/a-good-snowman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;a href=&#34;http://agoodsnowman.com/&#34;&gt;this game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an economic efficiency to the game&amp;rsquo;s design; no element is wasted. For example, there are no &amp;ldquo;screens&amp;rdquo;. Settings options appear as thought bubbles over the character&amp;rsquo;s head, and the map &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the puzzle. The benches which the character can sit on, along with other interactable environmental objects, initially seemed to be nothing more than neat touches with no gameplay impact, but were later revealed to be secret gateways. Even the humble reset button turned out to be a really important mechanic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in awe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme informs the mechanics really well, so much so that it&amp;rsquo;s truly difficult to imagine the game being built around anything else. Puzzles you&amp;rsquo;ve solved(&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; snowmen) are left intact, and monument-like. They lend a sense of permanence and significance to your actions, which is then challenged in the secret second-half of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good secret is hard to build, too.  Often, secrets are inserted into games almost for the sake of having them; they tend to be merely something for players to find. Like the reveal at the end of the film &lt;em&gt;the Prestige&lt;/em&gt;, I think a good secret changes your understanding of everything up till its discovery. I think this game has managed to pull it off in an organic and elegant way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a short and beautiful game. Ephemeral, like a snowman.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>