<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Controls on wetlag.com</title>
    <link>http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/tags/controls/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Controls on wetlag.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2015 20:37:48 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/tags/controls/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Feedback for Swipe Input</title>
      <link>http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/post/feedback-for-swipe-input/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2015 20:37:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/post/feedback-for-swipe-input/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I tried this game Heatos on my phone the other day, which involved swiping tiles around on a grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiles only moved  &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; you’ve completed a swipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Threes&lt;/em&gt; handles swipe input really well. The moment you start a swipe, the tiles move a little. You can slide your thumb or finger back and forth until you’ve decided to commit to a move, and the tiles will move in corresponding fashion.
Beyond providing feedback, it doubles as a preview of your intended action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when tiles can’t be moved, there’s a subtle stretch and squash effect to indicate so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is, there’s feedback throughout the entire duration of a swipe, not just at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lara Croft GO</title>
      <link>http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/post/lara-croft-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2015 07:47:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/post/lara-croft-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a fondness for the Tomb Raider series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I played the first four games in the franchise as my dad sat beside me and gave suggestions when I inevitably got stuck. We bought guidebooks and somehow still managed to get lost sometimes. The first guidebooks were black and white, and the screenshots weren’t very clear. I remember how excited I was when they were finally printed in colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lara Craft Go is the first Tomb Raider game I’d played since then and even though the gameplay was very different, it wafted nostalgia. It&amp;rsquo;s not just the radial menu and the occasional handstand. It&amp;rsquo;s that sense of wonder exploring ancient monuments filled with traps and treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s well executed, and gorgeous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanics were gently introduced, and then reused and recombined. For example:&lt;br /&gt;
-  Pressure plates could be deactivated by killing the creatures standing on them.&lt;br /&gt;
-  Torches that protected you against the creatures could also &amp;ldquo;push&amp;rdquo; them back onto pressure plates.&lt;br /&gt;
-  Pillars could stop rolling boulders, block dart traps, alter the creatures&amp;rsquo; paths. They could be pushed onto pressure plates, onto creatures, and onto other pillars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is a concept Jon Blow and Marc Ten Bosch called &amp;ldquo;compatibility of mechanics&amp;rdquo; in their &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/OGSeLSmOALU?t=2311&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;. (There are a few other &amp;ldquo;virtues&amp;rdquo; from the talk which applies to this game too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controls for this game surprised me; I had expected the character to move to where I tapped, like in Monument Valley. Diagonal swipes felt a little unnatural at first, but were easy enough to get used to. This may be the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a swipe-based control scheme in an isometric game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think something like the tracing controls in &lt;a href=&#34;http://wetlag.github.io/wetlag_blog/post/a-good-snowman&#34;&gt;A Good Snowman Is Hard To Build&lt;/a&gt; would have worked well in this game. With turn-based games like this, it usually takes a few moves just to perform that one action you have in mind. In your head you&amp;rsquo;re thinking &amp;ldquo;I want to push that pillar there.&amp;rdquo;, but it translates into &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt; to move to the pillar, and then &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;swipe&lt;/em&gt; again to move it to your destination. It&amp;rsquo;s a very subtle thing, but I think the inefficient mapping from thought to execution makes the experience less smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I surprised myself a little by enjoying this game, even if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t very challenging and many a time I was replaying levels and pixel-hunting for the secret vases in the game. (&lt;strong&gt;Aside:&lt;/strong&gt; It amazes me how strange and nebulous and even hollow I still find the concept of fun &amp;ndash; this subjective, swirling, conglomerate mess of even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; abstract concepts like entertainment, enjoyment, engagement, amusement, challenge, meaning, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first Tomb Raider game I&amp;rsquo;ve ever completed. No guidebooks too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>